Preliminary Guide to the Jules Prown Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jules David Prown papers
1954-2010
MS 1749
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
(10 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files and writings documenting the professional career of Jules Prown in the field of art history.
Prown, Jules David, 1930-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jules Prown, 1999, 2000, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 3 and 4 of the original accession are restricted until January 1, 2035 as established by Yale Corporation regulations. Box 5 is restricted until January 1, 2051 for the same reason.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Jules Prown, noted art historian and educator whose interests range from American colonial artwork to material culture, was born in Freehold, New Jersey, on March 14, 1930. He was graduated from Lafayette College in 1951 and earned masters degrees from Harvard University in Fine Arts and the University of Delaware in Early American Culture. In 1961, he obtained his doctorate degree from Harvard University, where he was the Edward R. Bacon Art Scholar. That same year, Prown went to Yale University as an instructor and later became the Paul Mellon Professor of the History of Art, a position he held until his retirement in 1999. He was involved in all aspects of art history, as a scholar, educator and curator. In addition to his academic achievements, Prown served as the curator of the Garvan and Related Collections of American Art at the Yale University Art Gallery and as director of the Yale Center for British Art from 1968 to 1976, a position he relinquished in favor of teaching and scholarship. Prown was an active member of the Yale community and served on a number of university committees and task forces.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files and writings documenting the professional career of Jules Prown in the field of art history.
Art historians; Art -- History; Painting, American; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Prown, Jules David, 1930-; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Personal, 1971-1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subject files
    - American Art, 1986-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Society for Eighteenth Century Studies, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Studies Association, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Art Bulletin, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Art Journal [American art issue], 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brazilian Congress of the History of Art, 1986-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - College Art Association of America
      - "Answering Questions the (American) Object Cannot Answer" session, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Distinguished teaching award, 1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Ethics committee, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Collins Illustrated Dictionary of Biography, 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Coolidge, John [correspondence], 1966-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dictionary of Art, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Foundation for Art Education, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Georgia O'Keefe Foundation, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hamilton, George [correspondence], 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Harvard University Press, 1967-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - International Congress of the History of Art [Art and National Ideas session], 1985-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - International Repertory of the Literature of Art, 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - J. Paul Getty Museum, 1985-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Kingery, David, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lectures, program proposals, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - London, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Material culture, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Montmouth Museum, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1972-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - National Humanities Institute, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - National Museum of American Art, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - National Portrait Gallery, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - New York Historical Society, 1989-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Nineteenth-century American art exhibition, 1976-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Oxford University Press, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Reader's reports, 1966-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Royal Society of Arts, 1972-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Smithsonian Institution ["Learning from Things" symposium], 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Stein, Roger [correspondence], 1983-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - University of Delaware, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Walpole Society, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Weinberg, Barbara, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Wellesley College [professorship and program in American Art], 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1975-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Williams College, 1980-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Williamsburg, 1980-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Yale-Smithsonian seminars on material culture, 1990-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - American Painting from its Beginnings to the Armory Show, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - John Singleton Copley, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Learning from Things, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Articles
      - "The Art Historian and the Computer; An Analysis of Copley's Patronage, 1753-1774", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - "Benjamin West and the Use of Antiquity", 1993-1996, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - "Benjamin West's Family Picture: A Nativity in Hammersmith", 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - "Copley, John Singleton" [ Dictionary of American Art entry], 1988-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - "The Expedition Against the Ohio Indians in 1764 under Colonel Bouquet: Two Early Drawings by Benjamin West", 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - "Mind in Matter", 1981-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - "A Note on Copley's Forge of Vulcan ", 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - "On Being a Client", 1981-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - "On the Art in Artifacts", 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - "The Promise and the Perils of Context", 1996-1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - "Raphaelle Peale, Fruits in A Silver Basket, 1814", 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - "Style as Evidence", 1976-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - "Thomas Eakins' Baby at Play ", 1983-1991 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - "Winslow Homer in His Art", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - "The Work of Art and Historical Scholarship", 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - Untitled [article about Thomas Sully manuscript notebooks], 1963 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Proposed articles, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Reviews, 1966-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Yale University
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials in boxes 3 and 4 are restricted until January 1, 2035 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - American Studies, 1969-1980 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Art Conservation, 1992-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Art Gallery Preprogramming report, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Arts Area Planning Study, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 71 - 74)
    - British studies, 1984-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Center for the Study of American Art and Material Culture, 1987-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Committees
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Teaching in Yale College, 1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - American Drawing and Watercolors Committee, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - Committee on Information and Technology, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Committee on Restructuring the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Printing Committee, 1972-1994 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - Victoria and Albert Museum, Bicentennial Exhibition Planning Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Expository writing program, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Graduate students/programs, 1968-1993 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Graphic arts collections, 1971-1996 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - School of Fine Arts, 1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Whitney Humanities Center Fellows, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Yale University Press, 1973-1998 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - York/Chapel Planning Study, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Searches
      Materials in box 5 are restricted until January 1, 2051 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
      - British Art Center, 1970-1975 (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Presidential search, undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-124
  - Subject files
    - Alumni show - American art, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - American Assembly [meetings of], 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - American Quarterly Review, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Expertise, 1968-1987 (Box 1)
    - Fourth International Congress on the Enlightenment, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Lectures, 1965-1984 (Box 1)
    - Skira Art Books, 1968-1980 (Box 1)
  - John Singleton Copley [research notes, background materials], 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1954-2010; Accession 2011-M-008
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1955-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, 1955-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C, 1955-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - D, 1955-2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - E, 1969-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - F, 1956-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - G, 1955-2006 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - H, 1955-2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - I, 1956-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - J, 1956-2005 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - K, 1955-2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - L, 1958-2009 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - M, 1957-2010 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - N, 1955-2009 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - O, 1967-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - P, 1955-2007 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - R, 1956-2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - S, 1955-2010 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - T, 1958-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - V, 1961-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - W, 1955-2009 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - X, Y, Z, 1976-2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subject files
    - American Antiquarian Society, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - American Art, 1999-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - American Art Center, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Art Library, 1967-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Boston Museum of Fine Arts (MFA), 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - British Studies, Circa 2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Coolidge, John, 1954-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Encyclopedia of Art, 1984-1985, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Glassie, Henry, Circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Houston Museum of Fine Arts, 1981-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Imaging America, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Rome, Circa 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Skira book, 1968-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Wolfe - Agnew, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Wolfe book, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)